Finding Aid for Gardner Ackley Papers, 1936-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- University of Michigan Files
  - 1930s-1950s
    - Miscellaneous research, reviews and study files
      - Review of The Basing-Point System of Fritz Machlup (Box 20)
      - Tax and Credit Aids to Industrial Development in Southern Italy: 1958 (Box 20)
      - Italian Research Project Notes (Box 21)
      - Relative Price Changes and Aggregate Consumer Demand: 1950 (Box 21)
      - Relative Price Changes and Aggregate Consumer Demand: early drafts (Box 21)
      - Information relating to project dealing with Aggregate Consumer Demand (Box 21)
      - Seminar presentation regarding National Income (Box 21)
      - Notes regarding Consumer Assets and Savings (Box 21)
      - Effects of Price Change on Aggregate Consumer Expenditure (Box 21)
      - Preliminary work on effects of price changes on aggregate consumer expenditure: 1949 (Box 21)
      - Effect of Relative Price Changes on Aggregate Demand (Box 21)
      - Future of Price-Controls (Box 21)
      - Congressional Hearings on Relationship of Prices to Economic Stability and Growth (Box 21)
      - Review of International Economic Papers No. 5, edited by Alan T. Peacock, et.al., 1955 (Box 21)
      - Business Cycle in U.S (Box 21)
      - Information about Inflation: 1958 (Box 21)
      - Techniques of Economic Forecasting (Box 21)
      - Review of The Theory of Inflation by Bent Hansen (Box 21)
      - Gardner Ackley doctoral dissertation manuscript (Box 21)
      - Aspects of Economic Theory of Administered Prices (Box 21)
      - Comments on "Some Structural Aspects of the Southern [Italian] Problem: The Complementarity of "Emigration" and Industrialization" by Vera Lutz: 1961 (Box 21)
      - Keynesian Analysis of Italian Unemployment Problem (Box 21)
      - Wage Price Relationship (Box 21)
      - Notes (Box 21)
      - Information Relating to Administered Price Study (Box 21)
      - Distribution of Business Income (Box 21)
      - "Economic Problems of an Atomic World" 1947 (Box 21)
      - "Financial Controls and Monopolistic Influences as they Affect location" and "Price Policies and Industrial Location" 1941 (Box 21)
      - Draft of Article regarding Spatial Competition in a Discontinuous Market (Box 21)
      - Information regarding Price Policies and Industrial location (Box 21)
      - Address, "The Challenge of Productivity" May 4, 1959 (Box 22)
      - Review of International Economic Papers No. 7 edited by Allan T. Peacock, et. al. (1959) (Box 22)
      - Review of Oligopolio e progresso tecnico by Sylos Labini (1957) (Box 22)
      - Administered Prices and the Inflationary Process (1958) (Box 22)
      - Paper "A Third Approach to the Analysis and Control of Inflation" (Box 22)
      - Multiplier Time Period (Box 22)
      - Inflation Control: 1950 (Box 22)
      - Relation of Price and Product Controls: 1950 (Box 22)
      - Consumer Assets and Consumer Savings: 1950 (Box 22)
      - Response to Gardner Ackley's article on Italian Tax and Credit Incentives by Kenneth Kaufman (Box 22)
      - "Price Policies and Industrial Locations" Notes and Text: 1941 (Box 22)
      - "Some Problems of Industrial Location Under The Defense Program" 1941 (Box 22)
      - Problem of Economic Instability in other Countries 1960 (Box 22)
      - Review of An Introduction to the Theory of Interest by Joseph W. Conrad (Box 22)
      - GNP Forecasting 1959 (Box 22)
      - Financial Analysis Seminar: 1956 (Box 22)
      - Economics 51-Lecture on Fiscal Policy: 1961 (Box 22)
      - Economics and Public Administration: 1954 (Box 22)
      - Long Run and Short Run Economic Outlook: 1954 (Box 22)
      - "Threats to Prosperity" May 1955 (Box 22)
      - Economics 52-Price Control and Markets: 1958 (Box 22)
      - "Period Analysis and Stability" 1959 (Box 22)
      - Location of Defense Industries: 1941 (Box 22)
      - Comment upon D.M. Wright's "Inflation and Equality" and responses to the comment (Box 22)
      - "The Relation of American Foreign Trade to the Problem of Farm Relief" 1936-1937 (Box 22)
      - Relationship Between Consumer Spending and Production (Box 22)
      - Graphs detailing relationship between Consumer spending and Production (Box 22)
      - "The Business Outlook" 1955 (Box 22)
      - Comment on "Liquidity Preference and Loanable Fund Theories" by Gardner Ackley, written by S.C. Tsiang (Box 22)
      - Review of International Economic Papers (Box 22)
      - Review of International Economic Papers No. 4 edited by A.T. Peacock, et. al (Box 22)
      - Review of Economic Changes: Selected Essays in Business Cycles by Simon Kuznets (Box 22)
      - Multiplier-Accelerator Growth Models (Box 22)
      - Proposals for stimulating post-war U.S. employment (Box 22)
      - Econometric Model of the Italian Economy: 1951-1959 (Box 22)
      - Problem of Capital Accumulation (Box 22)
  - 1960s-1980s
    - Correspondence
      - Department of Economics 1969-1981 (Box 28)
      - University administration 1962-1977 (Box 28)
    - Lecture notes, course outlines, and exams
      - Economics 201 and 400, lecture on macroeconomic policy November 30, 1977 (Box 28)
      - Economics 612, lecture notes, Winter 1979 (Box 28)
      - Economics 402, lecture notes, Fall 1982 (Box 28)
      - Economics 412, lecture notes, Winter 1982 (Box 28)
      - Economics 611, lecture notes, Fall 1983, 2 folders (Box 28)
      - Economics 402, 412, 611 and 612, exams 1971-1982 (Box 28)
    - Rackham Review Committee
      - Committee on Student Support Programs 1974 (Box 28)
      - Correspondence 1974-1976 (Box 28)
      - Dissertation Review Committee 1974 (Box 28)
      - Executive Board documents 1974-1975 (Box 28)
      - Final report May 7, 1975 (Box 28)
      - Meeting minutes 1974-1975 (Box 28)
      - Meeting notes 1974-1975 (Box 28)
      - Memoranda 1974 (Box 28)
      - Minority report May 19, 1975 (Box 28)
      - Questionnaire and responses (Box 28)
      - Rackham organizational data (Box 28)
      - Statement made at regents' meeting November 20, 1975 (Box 28)
      - Subcommittee on Evaluation (Box 28)
      - Subcommittee on Fee Structure (Box 28)
      - Subcommittee on Organization and Governance (Box 28)
      - Subcommittee on Research and Analysis (Box 28)
- Professional Correspondence
  The Professional Correspondence series is alphabetically arranged by correspondent and includes material on a wide variety of subjects. Most of this correspondence dates from the 1970s and 1980s.
  - A (Box 24)
  - American Economic Association (Box 24)
  - Anderson, James (Box 24)
  - Atlantic Institute (Box 24)
  - B, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Bean, Atherton (Business International) (Box 24)
  - Baker, Weeks and Co (Box 24)
  - Balanced Budget Amendment 1982 (Box 24)
  - Bellagio Center (Box 24)
  - Brookings Institution (Box 24)
  - C, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - D (Box 24)
  - Dun's Review (Box 24)
  - E (Box 24)
  - F (Box 24)
  - Fand, David and Sally (Box 24)
  - G (Box 24)
  - H (Box 24)
  - Humphrey, Herbert H (Box 24)
  - Heller, Walter (Box 24)
  - Hiromitsu, Ishi (Japan Project) (Box 24)
  - Johnson, Lyndon Baines (Box 24)
  - I-J (Box 24)
  - K (Box 24)
  - L (Box 24)
  - Livington, J.A (Box 24)
  - M (Box 24)
  - Mc (Box 24)
  - N (Box 25)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research 1977-1980 (Box 25)
  - National Economists Club 1967-1978 (Box 25)
  - National Science Foundation (Box 25)
  - Nourse, Edwin (Brookings Institution) (Box 25)
  - O (Box 25)
  - Okun, Art (Box 25)
  - P (Box 25)
  - Pechman, Joseph A (Box 25)
  - R (Box 25)
  - Reuther, Walter (Box 25)
  - S (Box 25)
  - T (Box 25)
  - University of Michigan 1968-1969 (Box 25)
  - University of Texas (Box 25)
  - V (Box 25)
  - W (Box 25)
  - Y-Z (Box 25)
- Meetings and Conferences
  Meetings and Conferences are alphabetically arranged by the sponsoring organization. Ackley organized the 1977 Brookings Institution conference on economic stabilization policy and files from this conference are especially detailed.
  - American Economic Association
    - Annual meetings 1980-1982, 3 folders (Box 25)
    - Executive committee meetings 1981-1984, 6 folders (Box 25)
    - Soviet exchange 1983 (Box 25)
  - Committee for Economic Development 1982 (Box 25)
  - Economic Dinner Group (Box 25)
  - Stabilization Policy Conference 1977 (Brookings Institution)
    - Brochure (Box 25)
    - Conference proposals, 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Correspondence with the Brookings Institution (Box 25)
    - Memos to participants (Box 25)
    - Papers
      - Ackley, Gardner (Box 25)
      - Barth, Hans (Box 25)
      - Basevi, Giorgio, et al (Box 25)
      - Cotta, Alain (Box 26)
      - De Wolff, Pieter and Driehuis, Wim (Box 26)
      - Renton, G.A (Box 26)
    - Papers (discussion of) (Box 26)
    - "Stabilization Policy" (paper by Ackley) (Box 26)
  - Trilateral Commission meetings 1978-1982 (Box 26)
- Speeches, Journal Articles, and Letters to the Editor
  Speeches, Journal Articles, and Letters to the Editor is the largest series in this accession and is chronologically arranged. In general, the contents list gives the subject and location of the speech. Titles of journal articles and subjects of letters are also usually included in the contents list.
  - Miscellaneous speeches, articles and letters 1951-1969, 3 folders (Box 26)
  - Undated speeches (Box 26)
  - Dun's Review 1971-1982 (columns written by Ackley) (Box 26)
  - Quarterly Report on the Economic Outlook 1970-1974, 2 folders (Box 26)
  - 1970
    - Albion College Convocation May 21, 1970 (Box 26)
    - Statement before the Joint Economic Committee July 22, 1970 (Box 26)
    - Memoranda for the Senate Democratic Policy Committee September 18, 1970 (Box 26)
  - 1971
    - "The Impact of Federal Government Expenditures", Conference Board Record January 1971 (Box 26)
    - Statement before the Joint Economic Committee August 31, 1971 (Box 26)
    - Notes for student-faculty forum on NEP September 16, 1971 (Box 26)
    - Federal Reserve consultants meeting September 23, 1971 (Box 26)
    - Letter to New York Times October 18, 1971 (Box 26)
    - Talk at Lyndon Baines Johnson Library October 18, 1971 (Box 26)
    - "The Impact of Price-Wage Stabilization: Present and Future", Hospital Financial Management Conference October 28, 1971 (Box 26)
    - Lecture on inflation policy November 2, 1971 (Box 26)
    - "Before and After Phase-Two" November 11, 1971 (draft of speech) (Box 26)
    - "The Economic Outlook in a Semi-Controlled Economy", Annual Bank Study Conference December 8, 1971 (Box 26)
  - 1972
    - Remarks before the University of Michigan Club of Chicago February 23, 1972 (Box 26)
    - Statement before the Joint Economic Committee February 25, 1972 (Box 26)
    - "The Future of Wage and Price Controls", lecture at Georgia State University February 29, 1972 (Box 26)
    - "An Incomes Policy for the 1970s", draft of article for Review of Economics and Statistics March 24, 1972 (Box 26)
    - "Phase Two and After: The Problem of Inflation Control", lecture at SUNY Brockport March 28, 1972 (Box 26)
    - "President Nixon's New Economic Policy: An Appraisal", lecture at De Paul University April 13, 1972 (Box 26)
    - "Observations on Phase-Two Price and Wage Controls", Brookings Panel on Economic Activity May 4, 1972 (Box 26)
    - Letter to the editor Atlantic Monthly September 28, 1972 (Box 26)
    - "Economic Issues in the 1972 Campaign", Chicago speech, October 5, 1972 (Box 26)
    - "Discussion of Economic Policies of Nixon vs. Mc Govern", lecture at the University Club, New York City October 12, 1972 (Box 26)
    - "Economic Policies in a Changing Society", conference in Newark, New Jersey October 18, 1972 (Box 26)
    - "Price Controls", Economics 731 lecture October 24, 1972 (Box 26)
    - Debate with Paul McCracken before Economics 201 October 30, 1972 (Box 26)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times October 31, 1972 (Box 26)
  - 1973
    - "The Role of the Economist as Policy Advisor in the United States", Essays in honour of Giuseppe Ugo Papi 1973 (Box 26)
    - Remarks for National Planning Process Symposium March 13, 1973 (Box 26)
    - "The Outlook for the U.S. Economy", remarks for American Statistical Association Forecasting Conference April 19, 1973 (Box 26)
    - Notes for discussion of current economic problems May 4, 1973 (Box 26)
    - "Recent Research on the Consumption Function", notes for talk at the Scientific Club May 12, 1973 (Box 26)
    - "Recent Inflation and Inflation Control in the United States", lecture at the Japan Economic Research Center July 19, 1973 (Box 26)
    - Remarks for Presidents Club annual meeting September 22, 1973 (Box 26)
    - "Inflation and Controls", remarks before the National Economists Club December 6, 1973 (Box 26)
  - 1974
    - "Prospects for the U.S. Economy: Growth or Stagnation?", Bureau of Business Research, University of Texas 1974 (Box 27)
    - Statement before the Joint Economic Committee February 20, 1974 (Box 27)
    - "Roles and Limits of Income Policy as an Economic Measure", Weekly Toyo Keizai, Tokyo February 22, 1974 (Box 27)
    - Brookings Institution study of the Japanese Economy April, 1974 (Box 27)
    - Remarks before the 1974 Midwestern Governor's Conference, July 29, 1974 (Box 27)
    - Statement before the Committee on the Budget August 14, 1974 (Box 27)
    - "Economic Realities", remarks before the American Bankers Association Governing Council meeting December 12, 1974 (Box 27)
  - 1975
    - "Two-Stage Recession and Inflation, 1973-1975", Economic Outlook USA January, 1975 (Box 27)
    - Statement before the Joint Economic Committee January 23, 1975 (Box 27)
    - Remarks before the Ann Arbor Rotary Club February 19, 1975 (Box 27)
    - "Recovery: How Soon? How Vigorous?", Economic Outlook USA, Spring 1975 (Box 27)
    - Remarks for Midwest Economics Association April 4, 1975 (Box 27)
    - "The Economic Health of the Nation", remarks for National Council on Social Welfare May 12, 1975 (Box 27)
    - "Some Observations on the 1976 Outlook and its Implications", Economic Outlook Conference, University of Michigan, December 12, 1975 (Box 27)
    - "The National Business Outlook for 1976", remarks before the Business and Economic Outlook Conference December 15, 1975 (Box 27)
  - 1976
    - "Fiscal, Monetary, and Related Policies" in Asia's New Giant: How the Japanese Economy Works, The Brookings Institution 1976 (Box 27)
    - Statement before the Joint Economic Committee February 5, 1976 (Box 27)
    - Remarks at the University of Michigan Residential College March 31, 1976 (Box 27)
    - Statement before the Committee on Banking, Housing and Urban Affairs of the United States Senate May 5, 1976 (Box 27)
    - "Advisers to Presidents: An Economic Exchange", Research News September, 1976 (Box 27)
  - 1977
    - "Import Prices, Domestic Inflation and Recession, and The Role of Stabilization Policy", Conference on Stabilization Policy May 5, 1977 (Box 27)
    - "Arthur Okun's New Tax-Based Incomes-Policy Proposal" Economic Outlook USA December 6, 1977 (Box 27)
    - "The Costs of Inflation", remarks at American Economic Association meeting December 28, 1977 (Box 27)
  - 1978
    - "Italian Economic Problems and Prospects", remarks before Economic Dinner Group January 16, 1978 (Box 27)
    - "New Perspectives on Inflation", remarks for Financial Executives Institute January 23, 1978 (Box 27)
    - Remarks to Economic Advisory Council to the Michigan Democratic Party Symposium February 18, 1978 (Box 27)
    - "The Nature and Cost of Inflation", remarks at the Scientific Club March 17, 1978 (Box 27)
    - "Italy in the 1970s 'Down the Drain to Bangladesh?'", remarks for Columbia University symposium, October 6, 1978 (Box 27)
    - Statement before the Joint Economic Committee June 16, 1978 (Box 27)
    - Letter to Congressman Giamo and Senator Muskie regarding Kemp-Roth bill July, 1978 (Box 27)
    - "Recent U.S. Inflation in Perspective", speech before Economic Outlook Conference November 16, 1978 (Box 27)
  - 1979
    - Interview for U.S. News and World Report January 15, 1979 (Box 27)
    - Review of William Fellner, ed., Contemporary Economic Problems in Journal of Money, Credit, and Banking February 1979 (Box 27)
    - Statement before House Committee on the Budget February 7, 1979 (Box 27)
    - Economists' open letter opposing a constitutional prohibition of deficits in the federal budget February 9, 1979 (Box 27)
    - Remarks before Moyers Symposium February 23, 1979 (Box 27)
    - Comments on paper by Lucio Izzo and Luigi Spaventa June 20, 1979 (Box 27)
    - "The Stabilization Policy Crisis of the 1970s", Saul Nelson lectureship, Oberlin College October 2-3, 1979 (Box 27)
    - Article for New York Times October 19, 1979 (Box 27)
    - "The Relationships among Behavioral Research, Theory, and Public Policy", comments for Institute for Social Research of the University of Michigan October 24, 1979 (Box 27)
    - "Our Aging Society", television interview on social security October 31, 1979 (Box 27)
    - "Adapting Social Security to a Changing Society", remarks to University of Michigan chapter of AAUP November 7, 1979 (Box 27)
    - Letter to the editor of the Wall Street Journal December 13, 1979 (Box 27)
  - 1980
    - "Inflation Remedies other than Conventional Fiscal and Monetary Policies", remarks for J.F. Kennedy School of Government January 28, 1980 (Box 27)
    - Remarks for Symposium of the Economic Advisory Council to the Michigan Democratic Party February 9, 1980 (Box 27)
    - Remarks for management education seminar on economics for decision-making February 18, 1980 (Box 27)
    - Statement before Senate Banking Committee March 10, 1980 (Box 27)
    - Comments on paper by James S. Duesenberry April 11, 1980 (Box 27)
    - "Inflation and Recession Policy", comments for panel discussion at the Western Economic Association June 16, 1980 (Box 27)
    - "The Economic Impact of the, 1980 Election", remarks before the American Association of University Women October 16, 1980 (Box 27)
    - "Providing Economic Advice to Government", speech for Conference in Honor of Walter W. Heller September 25, 1980 (Box 27)
    - "The Problem of Stagflation", paper prepared for Papeles de Economia Espanola November, 1980 (Box 27)
  - 1981
    - "The New Year and the New Administration's Economic Policy", paper prepared for Economic Outlook USA January 6, 1981 (Box 27)
    - Statement on the President's economic program given before the House Ways and Means Committee March 4, 1981 (Box 27)
    - "The Incomes-Policy Alternative", remarks prepared for a colloquium at The Conference Board June 10, 1981 (Box 27)
    - "The Outlook for Supply-Side Economics", talk given before the Illinois Economic Association October 30, 1981 (Box 27)
    - Remarks to business and professional group in Jackson, Michigan December 2, 1981 (Box 27)
    - Remarks given at the University of Michigan Law School senior day ceremony December 6, 1981 (Box 27)
  - 1982
    - Remarks at the University of Santa Clara January 18, 1982 (Box 27)
    - Statement before the House Committee on the Budget March 17, 1982 (Box 27)
    - Remarks at Eastern Economic Association Meeting April 29, 1982 (Box 27)
    - "Some Current Problems of the Social-Security System", notes for talk to the Scientific Club April 9, 1982 (Box 27)
    - Remarks given to the Ann Arbor Democratic Club May 11, 1982 (Box 27)
    - "Constitutional Limits on Federal Spending and Deficits", a commentary on Senate Joint Resolution 58 May 18, 1982 (Box 27)
    - Comments on draft of CED statement May 25, 1982 (Box 27)
    - Notes for talk given at Texas Christian University management seminar June 9, 1982 (Box 27)
    - Open letter on the Balanced Budget Amendment June 30, 1982 (Box 27)
    - "Constitutional Limitations on Federal Spending and Deficits", statement before the Committee on the Judiciary August 5, 1982 (Box 27)
    - "The Economic Outlook and Economic Policy", Economic Outlook USA, Summer 1982 (Box 27)
    - "Constitutional Limitations on Federal Spending and Deficits", Challenge November-December, 1982 (Box 27)
    - Review of Wage-Price Standards and Economic Policy by Jack A. Meyer December 3, 1982 (Box 27)
  - 1983
    - "Leviathan Redux", Rackham Reports January 23, 1983 (Box 27)
    - "Commodities and Capital: Prices and Quantities", American Economic Review March, 1983 (Box 27)
    - "Twenty-Five Years of Activist Economic Policies", speech before the National Association of Business Economists September 28, 1983 (Box 27)
    - Statement before the Administration and Rules, and Election Committee of the Michigan State Senate September 12, 1983 (Box 27)
    - "Some Uses Of Economics", Distinguished Senior Faculty Lecture Series given before the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts of the University of Michigan November 1-8, 1983 (Box 27)
    - Commentary for "Business Forum" section of the New York Times December 11, 1983 (Box 27)
    - "The Economic Outlook and Economic Policy", panel discussion notes for American Economic Association meeting December 21, 1983 (Box 27)
  - 1984
    - "The American Economy in 1985", remarks delivered at St. Norbert College September 28, 1984 (Box 27)
  - 1985
    - "Economic Policies for 1985", speech prepared for the series "The American Economy: Four Chairmen Speak" January 3, 1985 (Box 27)
  - 1987
    - "The Size and Economic Role of Government", essay in memory of Vittorio Marrama 1987 (Box 27)
- Chronological correspondence file
  The Chronological correspondence series dates from late 1964 to early 1968 and documents the period when Gardner Ackley was a member of the President's Council of Economic Advisers. This file consists of copies of outgoing correspondence only. As these files fall within the period when Ackley was a member of the President's Council of Economic Advisers, the researcher should also consult that series (boxes 4-18) for complementary materials.
  - December 1964-July 1966, 20 folders (Box 29)
  - August 1966-February 1968, 19 folders (Box 30)
- Clipping file
  The Clipping file covers the period of 1962 to 1984 and includes both articles about Ackley and his work on the CEA as well as articles on national economic issues and trends. This file should also be consulted in conjunction with the CEA files and the files from his service as ambassador to Italy.
  - 1962-1966, 6 folders (Box 31)
  - 1967-1970, 3 volumes; 1 folders (Box 32)
  - 1971-1984, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 33)
- Columns and unpublished writings
  Columns and unpublished writings includes copies of the column Ackley wrote for Dun's Review and Dun's Business Monthly as well as a chronological set of his unpublished papers, speeches, and various memoranda, formal lectures, and public pronouncements, most relating to the nation's economy.
  - "The Economy" column for Dun's Review and Dun's Business Monthly, October 1971-November 1984, 1 folders (Box 33)
  - Unpublished papers, speeches and releases
    - 1953-1990, 1 folders; 3 volumes (Box 34)
- US Ambassador to Italy 1968-1969
  The US Ambassador to Italy, 1968-1969 series documents the public face of Ackley's service as ambassador. In addition to copies of outgoing correspondence, there is briefing materials, interviews given, and an events/travel file accumulated from the various public functions he attended or at which he spoke. This series, in addition to speeches and travel materials, also includes many photographs from the events he attended.
  - Chronological correspondence file (outgoing copies only) 1968-1969, 4 folders (Box 35)
  - Washington briefing materials (Box 35)
  - Events file
    (include remarks made, trip materials, photographs, and briefing materials)
    - March 1968-December 1968 (Box 35)
    - January-June 1969 (Box 36)